Finding Aid for Gwendolyn S. Cruzat papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Gwendolyn S. Cruzat papers 1964-1990 1973-1976
Cruzat, Gwendolyn S.
1 linear foot
89160 Aa 2
Files of materials received from various University of Michigan committees and commissions on which she served, notably the Commission for Women, the Advisory Committee on Recreation, Intramurals and Club Sports, the Alumnae Athena Award Committee, and the University Club of Ann Arbor, Michigan.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated in 1988 by Gwendolyn S. Cruzat (Donor No. 7609 ). A second accession was received in 1993.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Gwendolyn S. Cruzat was a Professor of Information and Library Science at the University of Michigan. She began teaching at the University in the 1960s and retired in 1991. She also served as faculty representative on the Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics.
The Gwendolyn S. Cruzat Papers reflect her involvement with several committees dedicated to regulating university athletics and maintaining equality for both men's and women's athletics, notably the Commission for Women, the Advisory Committee on Recreation, Intramurals and Club Sports, the Alumnae Athena Award Committee, and the University Club of Ann Arbor, Michigan.
Subjects:
Cruzat, Gwendolyn S.; University Club of Ann Arbor (Mich.); University of Michigan. Advisory Committee on Recreation, Intramurals and Club Sports.; University of Michigan. Alumnae Athena Award Committee.; University of Michigan. Commission for Women.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Information and Library Studies.; College teachers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women college teachers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Students.
- Professional Papers
  - Advisory Committee on Recreation, Intramurals and Club Sports (ACRICS)
    Advisory Committee on Recreational, Intramural and Club Sports (ACRICS) (0.05 linear ft., 1967-1972) contains reports proposing the construction of both the North Campus Recreation Building and the Central Campus Recreation Building and outlining the specific athletic and recreational needs of the university community that the construction of these building would address.
    - Reports,1967-1972, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Alumnae Athena Award
    Alumnae Athena Award (0.05 linear ft., 1973-1977) contains committee proceedings, including the award agreement which outlines the history and purpose of the award and background material on women nominated for this award in 1974 and 1975.
    - Committee Proceedings,1973-1977 (Box 1)
    - Nominations,1974-1975, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Jones, Clara Stanton (Nominee), 1974/5 (Box 1)
  - Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics
    Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics (0.1 linear ft., 1987-1990) includes memoranda, agendas, and minutes documenting the issues and decisions made by the Committee on Academic Performance. This series also contains a manual prepared for members of the Board. The manual includes information on the structure of the Board and its committees, the Board's relationship to the Big Ten Conference, various University policies, and several organizational charts.
    - Academic Performance Committee,1987-1990 (Box 1)
    - Manual, undated (Box 1)
  - Commission for Women
    Commission for Women (0.4 linear ft., 1973-1974) documents this organization's inquiry into University of Michigan policies, procedures and practices which may contribute to discrimination against women. A manual includes Commission procedures and organizational charts. Also included are minutes which document the Commission's activities and concerns.
    - Manual (contains org. charts, agenda, etc.), 1971 (Box 1)
    - Minutes,1970-June 1974, 7 folders (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous,1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    Correspondence (0.1 linear ft., 1973-1990) documents Cruzat's role on the Board of Intercollegiate Athletics, Alumnae Athena Award Committee, and Commission for Women. Letters documenting the bitter dispute over awarding the prized "M" Award to women are also included.
    - 1973-1986 (Box 1)
    - 1987-1990 (Box 1)
    - Women's Athletic Award ("M" Award Controversy), 1975 (Box 1)
  - Minorities
    The Minorities (0.05 linear ft., 1964-1969) series includes correspondence and reports relating to the recruitment, appointment and utilization of minority group staff members in the University Library. Background material explaining the University of Michigan's Opportunity Award Program, in which minority students were actively recruited, is also included.
    - School of Library Science & University Librarians, 1969 (Box 1)
    - Opportunity Award Program,1964-1969 (Box 1)
  - State Relations Committee
    State Relations Committee (0.05 linear ft., 1979-1981) series includes correspondence and meeting minutes which document the activities of this committee charged with improving communication between the state of Michigan and the University of Michigan.
    - 1979-1981 (Box 1)
  - University Club of Ann Arbor
    The University Club of Ann Arbor (0.4 linear ft., 1971-1975; 1977-1978), of which Cruzat was a member of the board, includes minutes and reports outlining operations of this club which provides catering and entertainment services to its members (students, faculty and alumni).
    - Board Proceedings,1972-1978, 6 folders (Box 1)